这里是尼泊尔的索拉哈
Sauraha, Nepal.
这头印度犀并没有迷路
This rhino is not lost.
它是要去寻找食物
He is on his way to find food.
它必须穿过一个新出现的陌生世界
To get it, he must travel through a new
才能到达目的地
and alien world.
这头印度犀在它的一生中
This rhino, in his lifetime,
经历了先辈们无法想象的巨大变化
has seen more changes than any of his previous generations.
现在 全球各地的各类动物
Across the globe, animals of all kinds
都需要应对一个新的优势物种
are now contending with one newly dominant species –
我们人类
us.
和其它野生动物一样
Like so many wild creatures
印度犀也要学会适应人类社会
he's had to learn how to live in the human world.
有些动物改变了自己的行为模式
Some animals have changed their behaviour
学着利用人类社会的各种便利条件
to make the most out of living amongst us.
这些食蟹猕猴生活在巴厘岛
These long tailed macaques live in Bali.
人类游客的频繁造访
They have developed new interests,
促使它们养成了新的喜好
brought by human visitors.
每天早上
Every morning,
食蟹猕猴都会成群结队地
the troop heads for a building
前往领地中央的一座建筑
in the centre of their territory.
乌鲁瓦图神庙
Uluwatu temple.
这里每天都有大批游客前来参观
Tourists come here every day, in crowds.
整个神庙里到处都是机会
So the temple grounds are full of opportunities,
只要你知道去哪里寻找
if you know where to look.
这里有取之不尽的帽子
There is a constant supply of hats
和太阳镜
and sunglasses.
只要你掌握了突袭的技巧
And if you've mastered the element of surprise…
就可以轻松得手
it's easy to get them.
不过 它们不会把这些东西当作食物
But this harvest is not for eating,
而是为了交易
it's for bargaining.
买卖似乎很公平
Seems like a fair trade.
不过有些东西能换到更多的好处
But there are greater rewards to be had…
只有少数成员知道如何获取
for those who know how to get them.
这只年长的雄性食蟹猕猴似乎
And this old male appears to be doing…
深谙其道
very well.
它和族群中的其它长辈一样
He, and the other elders in this troop
有着丰富的经验
have both experience
和知识
and knowledge.
它们已经在这座神庙生活了10多年
They've been working the temple for over ten years
现在眼里只有那些重要的东西
and now concentrate on the big stuff.
盯着那些人类不可或缺的物品
Things that human beings just can't do without.
谁也不想光着一只脚走回家
No one wants to walk home with just one shoe.
而且这些家伙
And these old boys
已经迫不及待地将爪子伸向了尖端科技
can't wait to get their hands on the latest tech.
谁干的
Who's done that?
它们现在已经明白
They've worked out
人类不能没有手中的手机
that we simply can't survive without our phones…
还有钱包
or our wallets.
这些食蟹猕猴的雄性长辈还掌握了一些
The older males understand something
年轻后辈尚需要学习的知识
the youngsters have yet to learn.
那就是谈判的艺术
The art of the deal.
一根香蕉
A banana…
你好大的胆子
how dare you.
一块巧克力
A bar of chocolate,
这还差不多
that's better.
真正的技术蕴含在谈判的过程中
The real skill is in the negotiations.
食蟹猕猴这叫“以人之道 还治其身”
The macaques are playing us at our own game.
它们想要什么
They demand
就要什么
whatever they want.
人类的生活空间
Humanity has spread
已经扩展到世界的每个角落
to every corner of the globe.
我们已经成为影响自然界的强大力量
We have become a force of nature.
人类改变了80%的陆地面貌
We have altered 80% of the land's surface.
地球上的人口已经超过80亿
Eight billion people now live on this planet,
我们正在迅速改变周围的环境
and we are changing the world around us at such speed
对动物来说
that for animals
要跟上这种速度是极大的挑战
the challenge is to keep up.
这里是纽约市
New York City.
一群蚂蚁在活动
Ants.
专家认为
This particular species
这种独特的蚂蚁
is thought to have arrived here
是跟随欧洲第一批移民来到北美洲的
with the first European settlers.
现在 它们被称为铺道蚁
They are now known as pavement ants
在北美洲遍布人类生活的大小城镇之中
because they live almost exclusively our towns and cities.
铺道蚁数量的不断增加归因于食物垃圾
And they're thriving because of junk food.
百老汇大道上就有很多
And here on Broadway Avenue, there's a lot of it.
这是所有铺道蚁都想得到的口粮
This is what every pavement ant desires.
为了达到目的
And to get it
铺道蚁必须借助城市中
the ants use the cities thousands of miles
数千公里的地下通道
of underground tunnels.
侦察兵逐渐靠近目标
This scout is closing in on its target.
可使用人行道的另一种动物
But the animals with which they share the pavement
体重是它们的4000万倍
are forty million times their weight.
所以它们最好还是躲进缝隙里
So it's best to stay in the cracks.
运气真好
Jackpot…
一座肉山
a meat mountain.
但只身行动的铺道蚁
This is too big a job
无法完成如此艰巨的搬运任务
for just one ant.
与所有蚁群的工蚁一样
This worker is female
这只铺道蚁也是雌性
as they are in all ant colonies
它会在沿途留下信息素标记
and she leaves a trail of pheromones to mark a path.
在返回蚁巢的途中
She communicates with every sister she meets
它会把消息告诉遇到的每个姐妹
as she returns to the nest
于是信息很快传播开来
and news on the street spreads fast.
这块经过多次加工的肉
This ultra-processed meat
与它们原本的食物有很大的差别
is very different from their original food.
而铺道蚁强大的消化系统
But their digestive system
是它们成功的关键
is the key to their success.
它们可以快速适应
It's able to keep up with the way
人类不断变化的饮食习惯
humans constantly change their diet.
现如今 铺道蚁的大部分食物
Nowadays, the vast majority of what they eat
都是人类的加工食品
comes from human food.
仅在百老汇一条大街
On Broadway alone
铺道蚁每年吃掉的食物
pavement ants eat the equivalent of a staggering
几乎相当于60000个热狗
60,000 hotdogs every year.
一个热狗的热量
The calories in a single hotdog
可以保障整个蚁群一个月的能量所需
could fuel the growth of the entire ant colony for a month,
只不过它们先要保证能把热狗搬回家
if only they can get it back to the nests.
但因为行进缓慢
But this slow work
它们很容易吃亏
makes them vulnerable.
铺道蚁并不是唯一偏爱快餐的动物
They aren't the only ones partial to fast food.
要想获得食物就要争分夺秒
It's a race to get their prize home.
或许会有些许损失
There may be losses,
但铺道蚁种群得以不断壮大
but the colony as a whole will now thrive.
事实上 现在纽约市铺道蚁的数量
In fact, pavement ants are so successful here
已经达到了当地人口数量的1000倍
that they outnumber human New Yorkers 1000 to one.
但如果你恶名在外
But success in the human world
想要融入人类社会
can be harder to achieve
恐怕就没那么容易了
if your reputation precedes you.
这条身在印度的孟加拉眼镜蛇
Here, in India this cobra
正朝一座村庄爬去
is heading directly for a village.
它已经闻到了猎物的气味
It has detected the scent of prey.
这条孟加拉眼镜蛇身长大约两米
Nearly two meters long,
毒牙单次释放的毒液可以杀死10个人
it has enough venom in a single bite to kill ten people.
仅在印度 蛇类咬伤每年就会造成
Snake bites are responsible for nearly 60,000 deaths a year
近60000人死亡
in India alone.
它们爬行时悄然无声
They travel so silently
所以普通人很难察觉有蛇类靠近
that their presence is often undetected.
而它们捕猎时
And when they're hunting
可能会出现在任何一个角落
there's no place they won't go.
是一只蟾蜍
A toad.
孟加拉眼镜蛇能通过收吐分叉的舌头
Each tip of its forked tongue
收集猎物散发出的化学信号
collects chemical signals from the prey
确定目标的大致方位
and helps to reveal its position.
等靠近之后
But up close,
眼镜蛇就需要根据
the snake relies on movement
猎物的移动来准确定位
to precisely locate its prey.
蟾蜍必须谨慎选择逃跑的时机
The toad must pick its moment to escape.
蟾蜍每次碰触地面
Every time it touches the ground
都会留下气味痕迹
the toad leaves behind a scent.
它可以藏起来
It can hide
但眼镜蛇依然会循着线索逼近
but the trail will lead the snake to it.
这里不仅是孟加拉眼镜蛇的猎场
These cobras don't just hunt here,
也是它们生活的地方
they live here.
印度村庄
They have found a home
给孟加拉眼镜蛇提供了栖息之所
where the Hindu villagers revere them
当地村民会对它们敬若神明
and consider them to be demi-gods.
令人称奇的是
Remarkably,
科学家们认为村民的宽容
scientists believe that this tolerance
促使眼镜蛇的行为发生了变化
has led to a change in the snake's behaviour.
它们放缓了爬行速度
They move more slowly
在受到惊扰时攻击性也没那么强了
and are less likely to strike when disturbed.
眼镜蛇原本是地球上最令人生畏的动物之一
One of the most feared animals on the planet
但它们在这里却得到了人们的接纳
has found a place where they are accepted
与人类平和地生活在一起
and can co-exist with human beings.
不过对其它很多
But for many animals
生活在人类社会中的动物而言
living in the human world,
保持低调才是生存的要诀
it pays to keep a low profile.
在澳大利亚的墨尔本
Here in Melbourne, Australia,
有一种动物掌握了登峰造极的伪装技术
one creature has perfected the art of camouflage.
这是一只茶色蟆口鸱雏鸟
A frogmouth chick.
白天 它的爸爸会帮它做好伪装庇护
Its father helps to hide it during the day.
茶色蟆口鸱是夜行鸟类
They are nocturnal birds
夜幕降临后
and as day turns to night
成年茶色蟆口鸱离开巢穴
its parents come out of the shadows
趁着夜色开始在城市中搜寻食物
to reap the rewards of urban living.
照明灯光
The city lights
为它们的捕猎提供了绝佳的条件
create excellent conditions for hunting.
城市的每个夜晚
Every night in the city
都像满月时一样明朗
is as bright as when there's a full moon.
茶色蟆口鸱总能找到
So city Frogmouths often
足够的猎物喂养雏鸟
have their mouths full.
小家伙成长得很快
He's growing fast…
今天 它一直在淘气地动来动去
and today he just won't sit still…
接着 它突然打破伪装 暴露无遗
and now he has revealed his presence.
茶色蟆口鸱的首条生活准则是
The first rule of Frogmouth behaviour is
白天静止不动
don't move in the day…
但它们生命中总有一段时间
but this the one time in a Frogmouth's life
完全无法抑制自己飞翔的冲动
when the urge to fly simply cannot be suppressed.
不过 它还没有做好离开巢穴的准备
But he's not ready to leave home just yet.
又到了晚上
Come night-time
饥饿感再次袭来
he's hungry again…
茶色蟆口鸱雏鸟精神百倍
he's wide awake,
打算继续白天的尝试
and wants to take off where he left off.
它的行动引起了某些动物的注意
But he's getting unwanted attention…
但爸爸妈妈不在身边
and this time his parent is not nearby
没办法保护它
to protect him.
人类带出了自己的宠物
Humans bring pets
在澳大利亚
and cats in Australia
家猫每天可以杀死上百万只鸟类
kill a million birds a day.
这是它第一次展翅飞翔
His first proper flight,
小家伙必须找到一个休息的地方
but unless he can find a safe place to roost,
否则它的处境还是一样危险
he is still in peril.
成功了
Made it.
要想在城市里生存下去
But if he is to survive in the city
它必须和父母一样
like the adults
学会如何融入周围的环境
he'll have to learn how to blend in.
有些动物非常大胆
Some animals are so bold
甚至不屑于隐藏自己
that they don't even try to hide.
在高楼林立的城市中
To see a large predator in the built-up world
我们很少见到这种大型捕食动物
is a rare sight.
北美洲太浩湖附近的美洲黑熊
And here in Lake Tahoe, in North America,
体形似乎比同类更加健硕
these black bears are particularly big.
它们径直走向城镇的中心地带
And they're heading right to the centre of town.
冬天快要到了
Winter is approaching,
美洲黑熊必须在下雪之前
and these bears need to put on as much weight as possible
尽可能地增加体重
before the snow arrives.
这里可以享用到大量的食物
This is the great place to gorge.
俨然成为了美洲黑熊的理想王国
It's now bear country.
何必还要费力捕食呢
Why struggle for a meal…
穿过街道
when you can cross the street
就能轻松找到美味的餐点
for a takeaway.
城镇里有很多的食物
There's so much food here
一些美洲黑熊的体重
that some of the bears are 50% heavier
已经达到了乡间其它同类的1.5倍左右
than their country cousins.
当然它们没有止步于此
But why stop here?
一些美洲黑熊也想进屋里来用餐
Some bears just want to dine in.
有些动物很幸运
A lucky few
可以在人类世界轻松找到一顿美餐
are able to get an easy meal from the human world.
而人类到自然界中寻找食物资源时
But when we venture to the natural world in search of food,
其捕获规模可就另当别论了
the harvest is on a different scale.
短短40年的大规模捕捞
In just four decades
已经造成全球鱼类数量减少了一半
fishing reduced fish populations by half,
人类的捕捞
and created great problems
给原本以鱼类为食的海洋捕食动物
for the ocean predators
带来了巨大的麻烦
that once had such food to themselves.
在温哥华岛附近
Off the coast of Vancouver Island
大翅鲸栖息的海域
humpback whales inhabit waters
深受鲱鱼过度捕捞的影响
where herring have been over-fished.
众所周知
Humpbacks, however,
大翅鲸是一种非常聪明的动物
are renowned for their ingenuity.
12年前
Twelve years ago,
一头名叫康格的成年雄性大翅鲸
an adult male called Conger,
采用了一种全新的捕食方法
adopted a totally new way of feeding.
当海中鱼类的密度较低
When the density of fish in the water is low
鸟类纷纷潜入海中捕鱼的时候
and birds are diving to catch them,
康格就会浮到海面张开大嘴
the humpback opens its mouth
鱼类会将它看作可以躲避鸟类的庇护所
and creates a space that the fish mistake for shelter.
它们争先恐后地游进这个黑洞
The fish swim in
陷阱随即闭合
and the trap is closed.
康格是人类发现的
Conger was the first humpback whale
第一头使用这种方法的大翅鲸
to be seen doing this,
现在 附近海域已经有30多头大翅鲸
now 30 whales in the area
学会了使用这种策略
use the same technique.
温哥华岛附近的大翅鲸数量还在增加
The population of humpbacks here is growing,
或许大家认为
and you might think
这会造成鱼类数量的进一步减少
that this would reduce fish stocks even more,
但结果却出乎人们的意料
but something surprising is thought to be happening.
这种微小的浮游植物
These tiny phytoplankton
是整个食物链的基础
are the basis of the food chain
它们的生长需要一种关键元素
and need a vital ingredient to grow,
铁
iron.
鲸类的粪便含铁量很高
Whale faeces are rich in iron,
而巨型鲸类可以提供大量的粪便
and great whales produce it in enormous quantities.
于是浮游植物大量增加
So the phytoplankton flourishes
而这些正是鲱鱼的食物
and the herring feed on it.
事实上 鲸的粪便
Whale faeces in fact
有助于整个海洋生态系统的恢复
are helping to restore the whole ecosystem.
鲱鱼吸引来了更多的海鸟
The herring attracts sea birds.
有些鸟类潜入水下对鱼群发起攻击
Diving birds attack them from beneath,
而海鸥和鹱则从上方俯冲捕食鱼类
and gulls and shearwaters dive on them from above.
连白头海雕都能从盛宴中分得一杯羹
Even Bald eagles benefit from this rich feast.
令人惊讶的是
Astonishingly
虽然康格和其它鲸都会捕食鱼类
even though Conger and all the other whales are feasting on fish…
但它们也给海洋带来了丰富的养分
their role in fertilising the ocean is so influential,
因此专家估计鲱鱼的数量
that herring numbers here
不会减少 反而还会增加
are actually predicted to increase.
鲸给大海带来了活力
And the role they play in rejuvenating the environment
它给人类世界带来的影响更加意义非凡
is having an even greater impact on the human world.
浮游植物和陆地树木一样
The flourishing plankton also collects carbon
也可以吸收环境中的二氧化碳
from the atmosphere just as trees do.
由此估算 一头巨型鲸的影响
So much so that each great whale
甚至足以媲美
has the same impact
一片拥有30000棵树木的森林
as a forest of 30,000 trees.
巨型鲸类曾经遭到人类的大量捕杀
Our great whales were once hunted,
如果它们的种群数量
and if they returned
恢复到商业捕鲸开始之前的规模
to their pre-whaling numbers
那就相当于我们种植了
it's estimated that this would be equivalent to planting
超过300亿棵树木
over 30 billion trees.
如今 我们已经认识到
Whales are now being recognized
鲸类的存在对人类有益
as benefiting humanity.
但多数大型动物
But for most large animals
仍会因资源竞争而与人类发生冲突
competition with humans brings conflict.
这头6吨重的雄性非洲象正值壮年
This six tonne African bull elephant is in his prime.
要想在争夺交配权时占据上风
To stand the best chance of winning fights for females,
它就必须保持魁梧健壮
he needs to be big.
它根据气味判断
He can smell
周围有营养丰富的食物
highly nutritious food is near.
但是穿越边界到达那里
But crossing the boundary to reach it
需要承担很高的风险
is a dangerous journey.
必须等到夜幕降临才能行动
He must wait for the cover of darkness.
田里的肯尼亚农民
These Kenyan farmers
正在忙着为即将到来的夜晚做准备
are preparing for the night ahead.
过去两个月来 他们每天晚上
They have had to guard their crops every night
都要小心守护自己的农田
for the last two months.
还有两天就要收获了
With only two days until harvest,
此时绝对不能有闪失
this is a critical time.
一头雄性非洲象
In a single night
只需一个晚上就能毁掉
a bull elephant can destroy the entire crops
10位农民辛苦种植的庄稼
produced by ten farmers.
这头非洲象决定以身犯险
But he's taking a huge risk.
它的身高相当于成年男性的两倍
He's twice the height of a man
并不打算轻易就范
and he won't back down easily.
这样的人兽冲突
This human wildlife conflict
几乎每天晚上都会发生
happens night after night.
仅在肯尼亚
And each year
每年就有200头非洲象
it takes the lives of up to 200 elephants
和20人为此付出生命的代价
and 20 people in Kenya alone.
这样的对峙潜藏着巨大的风险
This stand-off is potentially lethal.
当地农民
The farmers
只能向经验丰富的巡护员寻求帮助
have had to call for help from a team of highly experienced rangers.
他们虽然带着武器
Although they're armed,
但目的只是把非洲象赶出农田
their task is to drive the elephant out of the field
不会伤害对方
without harming it.
然而雄性非洲象非常固执
But the bull is determined
就是不肯走
to hold ground.
巡护员只能继续向它逼近
The rangers will have to get closer.
他们快步靠近
On foot.
迫不得已之下
The rangers have to resort
他们动用了爆竹驱赶非洲象
to firecrackers.
雄性非洲象终于离开农田
The bull is driven from this the field
向灌木丛深处跑去
and retreats deep into the bush.
这头雄性非洲象很幸运
Fortunately for this bull
冲突以和平方式解决
the battle has been resolved peacefully.
这些策略和努力
And efforts like these
避免了对非洲象造成伤害
are seeing fewer elephants killed
肯尼亚的非洲象数量又开始增加了
and their population in Kenya is starting to rise again.
不过由于人类对全球气候的巨大改变
But conflict with wildlife is now occurring on a far greater scale
导致我们与野生动物之间的冲突规模
as a consequence of the way we are changing
也在不断升级
the world's climate.
一些干旱地区迎来了罕见的暴雨
Some arid regions are now experiencing unusually high rainfall.
这对非洲东北部地区的
And that is good for growing crops
粮食种植确有帮助
here in North Eastern Africa.
但也给一种昆虫
But it also the perfect conditions
提供了便利条件
for one particular insect.
它们就是沙漠蝗
Desert locusts.
沙漠蝗通常独居
They're normally solitary creatures,
但若从沙土中孵化的数量激增
but emerging from the sand in great numbers
它们连外观都会发生变化
triggers a dramatic physical change.
沙漠蝗的身体变成了鲜艳的黄色
They turn a vivid yellow
并且开始成群活动
and become highly social.
庞大的沙漠蝗群
Together
俨然成为一支势不可挡的昆虫大军
they are an unstoppable army.
它们先是爬行
On foot
每天可以前进一两公里
they can cover a mile a day.
但爬行毕竟有很大的局限性
But they can only go so far in this way.
它们必须寻找一处更高的地方
They need to find height.
聚集到高处后
Up here
沙漠蝗终于开始了最后的羽化
they begin their final transformation.
单只沙漠蝗通常需要至少一个月
Normally it takes an individual insect
才能发育为成虫 长出翅膀
at least a month to become a winged adult,
可聚集成群后
but in their social form,
它们的成熟速度大大加快了
their development speeds up.
现在 它们只需要等待翅膀变硬
Now, all they need is for their wings to harden.
沙漠蝗一旦飞入空中
Once airborne
每天就能行进近100公里
they can travel 60 miles in a day.
成群的沙漠蝗遮天蔽日 造成蝗灾
Swarms merge and they become a plague.
这群沙漠蝗的数量足有几十亿只
This one contains billions of individuals
每天吃掉的粮食数量
and eats as much in a day
几乎相当于德国人口的总消耗量
as the entire population of Germany.
如今 在非洲东北部地区
Today, in North Eastern Africa,
由于气候变化的影响
as a consequence of climate change
蝗灾变得越来越频繁了
devastating surges of locusts are becoming more frequent.
人与动物的世界发生着激烈的碰撞
Two worlds are colliding.
人类在无意之间为沙漠蝗的大规模繁殖
Unintentionally, humanity has created exactly the conditions
创造了有利条件
that cause this species to explode in numbers.
不过还有一类动物
But another group of animals has seen
也会出于人为原因
an even more dramatic rise
出现数量急剧增加的情况
as a consequence of our actions.
我们人类让地球上几种特定动物的数量
We have increased the numbers of a few species,
出现了几何级的增长
almost astronomically.
就重量来说
By weight,
全球70%的鸟类
70% of the world's birds
都是我们熟悉的鸡等家禽
are now chickens or other domesticated fowl.
人类每年蓄养的牲畜和家禽数量
We rear 70 billion
已经达到700亿左右
farm animals each year.
每一只个体都需要食物供应
And every one of them needs feeding.
这么多的家禽和家畜需要大量的饲料
Producing the food for such numbers of domesticated animals
相关产业给自然界造成了重大影响
is having a profound impact on the natural world.
亚马孙雨林的面积
The Amazon rainforest,
相当于印度国土面积的两倍
twice the size of India.
亚马孙雨林资源极其丰富
It's so rich,
物种数量相当于全球总量的十分之一左右
it contains one in every ten species on the planet.
这只树懒和它10个月大的幼崽
And it's home to this sloth
就以这里为家
and her ten-month old baby.
树懒幼崽出生的这片密林
He was born into an environment
以往几乎没有人类出现
virtually untouched by humanity.
但是现在
But now
这里已然开始被人类占据
human beings are claiming even this space.
我们每年在亚马孙地区
Year after year
砍伐的雨林超过200万公顷
we clear over two million hectares of the Amazon forest,
相当于整个威尔士的面积
an area the size of Wales.
这些砍伐后的土地
And we use nearly all of it
几乎全部用来放牧
to make more space for cattle
或者种植大豆为牲畜提供饲料
and to grow soya to feed our livestock.
如今 栖息地破坏
Today, habitat destruction
已经成为人类给全球野生动植物带来的
is the biggest problem we have created for wildlife
最大生存难题
around the world.
这头卷尾豪猪幸运地逃过了一场火灾
This porcupine has survived the fire.
它得到了人类的救助
And is being rescued.
它会被送往另一片原始森林
It's being relocated to pristine forests.
这里就是它的新家
This will be its new home.
只有少数幸运的动物
Only a fortunate few animals
能得到第二次生命
are being given such a second chance.
健康的自然环境
A healthy natural world
对野生动物来说至关重要
is not only vital for wildlife,
也是我们人类长久生存的必要条件
but for our own very existence.
我们必须想办法重新恢复自然平衡
Somehow we must find ways to redress the balance.
目前全球大部分的农业用地
Currently, the vast majority of agricultural land,
超过75%
more than 75%,
都是用来饲养禽畜
is used to raise livestock,
这种模式效率很低
and this is very inefficient.
我们可以找到解决方法
There are solutions,
第一种是考虑改变饮食结构
one is considering what we eat.
如果大家少吃肉食和牛奶
If we shift away from eating meat and dairy
多吃蔬菜等素食
and move towards a plant-based diet,
那么太阳能就可以直接转化为人类的食物
then the sun's energy goes directly into growing our food…
这种方式更加高效
and because that's so much more efficient,
我们完全可以生产出足够的粮食
we could still produce enough to feed us…
而且只需当前四分之一的农田就好
but do so using a quarter of the land.
我们由此节省出的农业用地
This could free up an area the size
相当于美国 中国
of the United States, China,
欧盟和澳大利亚面积的总和
the European Union, and Australia combined.
这些空间都可以重新回归自然
Space that could then be given back to nature.
人类的创新
And human innovations
或许可以为野生动物的生存做出更大的贡献
may be able to do even more for wildlife.
现在的高科技农业可以垂直种植作物
High tech farms now grow plants vertically,
单位面积的粮食产量
yielding up to 350 times
可以提升到原来的350倍左右
the food grown in the same area.
这只是我们的众多解决方案之一
This is one of many solutions we already have,
还有很多其它方案有望推广
and others are surely on the horizon.
要找到方法保护地球上的所有生物
To find ways to protect all life on Earth
我们就必须重新规划人类未来的生活模式
means re-imaging how we live on this planet in the future.
人类有聪明才智
Human ingenuity –
一定能找到合适的解决方法
our extraordinary ability to find solutions –
我有信心一定能成功
gives me hope that we can.
这将是当前和下一代人
It will be the major challenge
必须面对的首要问题
for this generation and the next.
为了拍摄火灾对亚马孙雨林的影响
To film the impact that fires are having on the Amazon
《地球脉动III》摄制组
the Planet Earth III team
加入了当地的志愿消防队
joined a local volunteer fire-brigade.
这支消防队要前往
The fire-brigade are responding to a patch
这次雨林火灾的主要区域
of primary rainforest that is burning.
现在火灾已经持续了两天
It's been burning for two days now,
很难想象我们会看到怎样的场景
it's difficult to know what we're going to see.
这些火灾通常是非法纵火造成的
The fires are mainly lit illegally…
目的是腾出空间用来饲养牲畜
to clear space for cattle.
火灾很严重
It's really intense.
看那边的火情
Look at the fires over there.
我以前从没见过这样的景象
I've never seen anything like that before.
快点 用水泵
Come on, use the water pump!
离远点
Do it from far!
压住那个区域的火势
Stop that fire on the corner!
对抗火灾是一项危险的工作
Battling fires is dangerous work,
但消防员每天都要面对这样的情况
but the firefighters face them every day…
对野生动物摄制组来说
for the wildlife film crew
这是一次全新的体验
this is a totally new experience…
而火情的发展完全无法预料
and these fires can be unpredictable.
尼尔 别在那里待太久
Neil, don't spend long in there.
我们得小心一点 别让大火烧到这边
We need to be careful so the fire doesn't get here.
现在的风向很危险
The way the wind is right now it's dangerous.
我们得赶快离开
I think we've got to run.
我去取延时摄像机
I'll get the timelapse.
往这边跑
Run this way!
太可怕了
It's quite scary.
地面摄制组撤离之后
With the ground team retreating,
最安全的拍摄方式就是使用无人机
the safest way to carry on filming is with the drone.
无人机弄丢了吗
Have we lost the drone?
阿比好像看见了 她已经过去了
Eh I think Abi has seen it, Abi's on her way.
你是去找无人机了吗 阿比
Can you confirm you're on your way to the drone Abi?
无人机飞到了大火上方
The drone has gone up in flames.
我拿到无人机了
I have the drone.
它在我们面前坠毁了
It crashed in front of us.
它着火了
It was on fire.
无人机已经损坏 无法修复了
The drone is damaged beyond repair.
别担心 真的 别担心无人机
Don't worry about it, I mean don't worry about it.
没事
It's absolutely fine.
可机器坏了
They are not OK.
真的 没关系 只是一台机器
It is. It's ok, it's equipment
我们还有一台备用的
we've got a spare.
重要的是 我们都很安全
The main thing is we're all safe,
没有人受伤
no one's hurt.
团队集合到一起
The team re-group,
决定离开火灾的中心
and decide to move away from the heart of the fire
转移到边缘地带
to its fringes
寻找被大火困住的动物
to look for animals caught up in the flames.
报告说有只猴子被困在这片树林
There's been reports of a monkey in the trees.
问题是这边沿线都有火情
The problem is there's fires all the way along here,
这边也是
as well as all along here,
所以很难确定这些野生动物会做什么
so it's hard to know what all this wildlife is going to do
它们的家都被大火烧光了
when their home is burnt up like this.
我不知道雨林中的动物遇到火灾
I don't know what it's like for these rainforest animals
会是一种什么样的感觉
to be experiencing a fire,
我自己都觉得很可怕 所以
it's horrific for me so
很难想象它们是什么感受
I don't know what it is for them.
大火一直持续到当天晚间
The fires burn into the night.
第二天
The following day
摄制组和消防员一起出发
the crew accompany the firefighters
到大火过后的森林里展开搜救
in the search for animals in the aftermath.
我的天哪
Oh my god,
蚁巢里面也着火了
there are flames all inside of it.
看那些白蚁
The termite,
老天哪
oh, my god.
一些动物奇迹般地活了下来
Remarkably, some animals have survived.
我感到很痛心
For me, it hurts a lot
因为大自然和我们一样都有生命
because nature is alive, just like we are.
人类的特性 大自然也都具备
Everything that we have, it has too.
看到森林变成这样真的很难过
so it's sad to see the forest like this.
它应该得到保护
It deserves more,
不应该被这样对待
it shouldn't be treated like this.
大自然强大
It must be strong
才能给予我们力量
to give us strength
如果它虚弱无力 我们也会感到虚弱
because if it gets weaker, we will feel weaker
如果它倒下了 人类也会灭亡
and if it falls, we all fall.
清理林地用来放牧
Clearing land for farming
并不是亚马孙地区独有的问题
is not a problem unique to the Amazon.
农业用地现在已经占到
Agriculture now takes up
全球可居住土地的大约一半
half of the habitable land on the planet.
我们必须找到新的方法
To produce food with less impact on the natural world
减少粮食生产过程对自然界的影响
requires new approaches
为此 摄制组来到了一个农场
and that lead the wildlife film crew to a farm
而它却在一座仓库里
in a warehouse.
我们来到了城市中央
We're in the middle of a city
难以想象这么多食物
I can't believe so much food been grown
能生长在这么小的空间里
in such a small space.
在距离亚马孙雨林
Here in Los Angeles,
9000多公里的洛杉矶
6,000 miles from the Amazon,
这座新奇的农场
this farm is part of a
就是人类粮食革命的前沿阵地
burgeoning food revolution.
这是全球产能最高的农场
This is the most productive farm in the world
我们的目标就是
and it's our goal
将种植业的土地和资源使用量
to reduce the amount of land and resources necessary to grow,
降到最低
down to the bare minimum.
我们花了很长时间才明白
It took a while to understand that
对大自然而言 农业用地
for nature agriculture use of land
是人类破坏环境的主要原因
was the primary destructive behaviour of humanity.
随着这种种植方式的推广
As we expand this means of growing,
希望可以通过这种方法
I'm very hopeful that this approach
最终能让大量土地回归自然
can ultimately give a lot of land back to nature
让地球恢复原有的生物多样性
and allow that biodiversity
继续繁荣发展
to re-establish and flourish.
这座农场不仅缩小了占地面积
Not only does this farm use less space
灌溉用水量也同时缩减了90%
but it also uses 90% less water,
而且不使用农药
no pesticides
还减少了食物里程
and cuts food miles.
我认为这是个很好的开始
It does feel like a really good start.
类似这样的创新
Ideas like this
可以减少人类对地球的影响
can reduce our footprint on the planet,
希望大自然可以由此重焕生机
giving the natural world a chance to bounce back.